Guide to the Vincent Callahan Collection 1962-2008
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
Vincent Callahan collection
1962-2008
C0299
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
3.0 linear feet (8 boxes)
This is a collection of newspapers and articles collected by Vincent Callahan pertaining to his long career and political activities.
Callahan, Vincent F., Jr., 1931-2014
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Yvonne Callahan on November 15, 2016.
Biographical Note
Vincent F. Callahan Jr. was a Republican party member from Northern Virginia that represented Fairfax County in the state legislature. He served for 40 years before retiring in 2008 until he passed away as a result of complications from West Nile virus. Callahan was first elected in 1967 as one of only 14 Republicans out of 100 representatives, with the Republicans becoming a majority by the time of his retirement. In 1972 he was elected to the Appropriations Committee, where he would eventually become the first Republican to head the committee in many years.
Many of his accomplishments benefitted his native Northern Virginia, as he worked to make sure the region was not only not forgotten but expanded upon. He is credited for the expansion of the Dulles Corridor as well as the funding of the Wolf Trap Center. He was also influential in the growing George Mason University.
He did not always see eye-to-eye with the conservative direction the party was moving in as the decades went, preferring to be a moderate and work to compromise with both sides whenever possible. This led to his being well liked on the floor of the Virginia House.
Scope and Content
The Vincent F. Callahan Jr. collection consists primarily of local newpaper clippings, magazine clippings, photographs, and various invitations and awards that Callahan collected over the course of his political career. The content ranges from the late 1960s to the mid-2000s when Callahan retired. The materials in the collection pertain almost entirely to local Northern Virginia news and events that he was directly involved in. Topics range from Callahan's campaigns to get elected and re-elected, tax issues across the state, events in Northern Virginia and across the state, projects he has helped secure funding for, and invitations to political events. While the majority of the material was not created by Callahan, included also are several writings of his that were submitted to papers or were part of his newsletters. These range from the "Callahan and the Capital" newsletter to the "House Call" column run in the McLean Providence Journal, as well as responses he made to his opponents in papers. Over the course of his political career Callahan had opportunities to travel internationally and locally for major events, attending the inaugurations of President Nixon and many other events that shaped local and national history that have appearances in this collection. One box consists of many newspaper clippings sorted into scrapbooks put together by the Callahan family. The remaining boxes are loose clippings and other materials sorted into folders organized by publication. Some parts of the collection, such as The Washington Post and the Washington Times, were not kept due to the ease of access online.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Related Material
This Special Collections Research Center also holds the papers of other Virginia state legislators, including and.
Index Terms
Persons:
Holton, A. Linwood (Abner Linwood), 1923-
Geographical Names:
Virginia, Northern--Politics and government.; Virginia--Politics and government--20th century.
Document Types:
Newspapers.; Scrapbooks.
Contents List
  - Arlington Catholic Herald and News, 1970s, 1996-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Assorted Invitations, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Events and Galas Callahan was invited to at different times
  - Assorted Papers, 1971-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    AP articles and unmarked clippings
  - Awards and Honors Received, circa 1960s-80s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Bee, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business Journals, 1986, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Callahan at the Capital, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campaign Materials, 1960s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Capitol Reports, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Christmas Cards, circa1960s-80s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Connection (1 of 2), 1989-99 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Connection (2 of 2), 2000-07 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Daily Progress, 1983-87, 2001-02 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Daily Press, 2001-06 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Evening Star and Daily News, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Free-Lance Star, 1984, 2003-07 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Fairfax Journal (1 of 6), 1969-79 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Fairfax Journal (2 of 6), 1980-84 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Fairfax Journal (3 of 6), 1985-89 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Fairfax Journal (4 of 6), 1990-95 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Fairfax Journal (5 of 6), 1996-99 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Fairfax Journal (6 of 6), 2000-04 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Fairfax Star, 1976-81 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Gazette, 1974-89, 1994-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Globe, 1969-79 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Herndon Newspapers, 1971-77, 1994-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Human Events, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Presidential Inaugurations, 1969-73 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Governor Inaugurations, 1970-86 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Local Star, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Magazine Cuttings, 1970s-80s, 2000-05 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Marketplace, 1973-76 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - McLean News, 1974-75 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The McLean Providence Journal (1 of 6), 1969-74 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Newspaper went through multiple name changes: McLean Providence Journal, Providence Journal and Fairfax Herald, Great Falls Current, Times Community Newspapers, McLean Times
  - The McLean Providence Journal (2 of 6), 1975-79 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The McLean Providence Journal (3 of 6), 1980-89 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The McLean Providence Journal (4 of 6), 1990-94 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The McLean Providence Journal (5 of 6), 1995-99 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The McLean Providence Journal (6 of 6), 2000-06 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - News-Advertiser, 1981-83 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, 1982-99 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Northern Virginia Daily, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Northern Virginia Sun (1 of 8), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Northern VA Sun (2 of 8), 1971-75 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Northern VA Sun (3 of 8), 1976-79 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Northern VA Sun (4 of 8), 1980-85 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Northern VA Sun (5 of 8), 1986-89 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Northern VA Sun (6 of 8) "House Call", 1986-89 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Regular column written by Callahan
  - Northern VA Sun (7 of 8), 1990-99 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Name change to "The Sun Gazette"
  - Northern VA Sun (8 of 8), 2000-07 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photos, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Progress-Index, 1988, 97, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Redistricting, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Republican Caucus, 1969-85 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Republican News Publications, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Reston Times, 1974-81 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Richmond News Leader, 1969-91 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Richmond Times-Dispatch (1 of 2), 1969-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Richmond Times-Dispatch (2 of 2), 2000-07 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Roanoke Times, 1969-73, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Springfield Independent, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Sound, 1969-79, 86 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Washington Daily News, 1969-72 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Washington Examiner, 2006-07 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Washington Jewish Week, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Washington Star, 1975-81 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Washington Star-News, 1973-75 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Winchester Star, 1993, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Delegate, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Pilot/Ledger Star, 1970s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Sentinel, 1969-74 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Times, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Warner 2008 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Mark Warner's 2008 Campaign
  - 1 Scrapbook, 1964-65 (Box 6)
  - 3 Scrapbooks, 1965-68 (Box 7)
  - 3 Scrapbooks, 1962-69 (Box 8)